And welcome back to More Leaderboard Fest as we go through some more leaderboards.
다시 리더보드 페스티벌입니다 리더보드를 더 살펴보죠
But this time we're bringing into the mix open source and closed source models together on some of the
하지만 이번에는 상위 리더보드에서 믹스 오픈 소스와 비공개 소스 모델을 함께
leading leaderboards.
가지고 올 거예요.
Outside hugging face for for a change.
밖에서 얼굴이나 안아주고요
We are actually not going to be looking at hugging face now.
이제 포옹은 안 할 거예요
So the first leaderboard that I want to show you, that is another one that is definitely belonging
첫 번째 리더보드를 보여드릴게요 이것도 분명히 여러분 책갈피에 들어갈
on your bookmarks is the vellum leaderboard.
거예요 피지 리더보드죠
We did touch on this briefly in the past.
과거에 잠깐 언급한 적이 있죠
Uh, vellum AI company had publishes this essential resource for LM practitioners, which compares different
피지 인공지능 회사는 LM 종사자들을 위한 필수 자료를 발표했고 페이지 맨 위에 있는
models at the very top of the page.
다른 모델을 비교했어요
You get these comparison charts about some basic benchmarks that are some of the easier benchmarks these
비교 차트가 있는데 기본 벤치마크에 관한 거죠 요즘엔 쉬운 벤치마크예요
days.
MLU는 추론이고 Pro는 아니고 기본 수치예요 소금 한 꼬집이지만
metric, but still, it's still quoted a lot.
여전히 많이 인용되죠
Um, human eval for Python coding and math.
파이썬 코딩과 수학에 대한 인간 평가예요
Um, and what you're seeing here are generally the closed source models that you know and love, like
여기서 보시는 건 일반적으로 비공개 소스 모델입니다 여러분이 잘 알고
GPT four and sonnet 3.5, sonnet and GPT turbo and four.
사랑하는 GPT 4, 소넷 3처럼요 5번 소네트와 GPT 터보 그리고 4번요
But look at that.
저것 좀 보세요
There is an open source model in the mix in the form of llama 3.1 4.05 billion.
혼합물에 llama 3 형태의 오픈 소스 모델이 있어요 1분 4초 5억 5천만 달러요
That is the largest open source model on the planet.
지구상에서 가장 큰 오픈 소스 모델이죠
And you can see that it is competing, competing favorably with some frontier closed source models.
보다시피 일부 비공개 소스 모델과 호의적으로 경쟁하고 있어요
Uh, so it does appear that this is in order of strength with the strongest one first, GPT four zero,
현재 가장 강력한 팀이 선두를 달리고 있습니다 GPT 40, MLU가
uh, crushing it with MLU.
압도적으로 앞섰죠
But you can see that llama 405 B is just fractionally behind.
하지만 라마는 405B에 살짝 뒤처져 있어요
Um, and they're all neck and neck.
다들 막상막하예요
Really?
정말요?
Uh, so, uh, obviously llama 4 or 5 billion is the open source model is very much a contender.
라마는 40억 혹은 50억 개로 오픈 소스 모델이 강력한 경쟁자죠
Then when it comes to coding, you can see that this is the order.
코딩을 할 때는 이 순서가 보이시죠
Clause 3.5 sonnet is the leader, then GPT four zero, then llama 405 be in third position, and then
3항을 보세요 5 소네트가 선두 그다음은 GPT 405 그 뒤는 라마 405 미니
the mini version of GPT four zero.
버전 GPT 405가 3위죠
Not not far off given how much cheaper it is.
얼마 안 되는 것 같아요 훨씬 저렴하니까요
And then GPT turbo.
GPT 터보도 있죠
And then here is the ranking for math questions GPT four zero at the at the helm, followed by llama
GPT 수학 문제 순위표입니다 GPT는 4-0이었고 그 뒤에는 라마가 4,050억
405 billion right after that, and then followed by the others, with Claude coming in fourth place.
달러였죠 그 뒤로는 다른 순위표들이 나왔고 클로드가 4위를 차지했어요
For those top models, here are some super useful charts on performance.
그런 톱모델을 위해 아주 유용한 실적 차트를 보여드릴게요
A little bit easier to interpret than the multi-dimensional chart we saw in Hugging face, although
얼굴 안기 때 봤던 다차원 차트보다 해석하기가 좀 더 쉽죠 물론 비트는
less information, of course.
더 적지만요
Uh, so in terms of the speed, the fastest to generate tokens measured in tokens per second is llama
속도 측면에서 보면 초당 토큰으로 토큰을 가장 빨리 생성하는 건 라마다 80억 오픈
8 billion open source model.
소스 모델이에요
Not surprising because of course with fewer parameters it's doing less, so probably worth understanding.
당연하죠, 매개 변수가 적을수록 작업량도 less니까요 그러니 이해할 가치가 있죠
Uh, yeah.
네
I see.
그렇군요
So.
그래서요?
So this is all, uh, trying as much as possible to run in a consistent way.
최대한 일관되게 달리려고 노력하는 게 중요해요
And the information explains a little bit more about that.
비트에 대한 정보가 조금 더 설명해줘요
Uh, so after llama eight comes llama 70, a bigger model, and then Gemini 1.5 flash.
라마 8 다음은 더 큰 모델인 라마 70 그리고 제미니 1호예요 5번 섬광이에요
Uh, and then Claude, three haiku, and then GPT four.
클로드, 하이쿠 3개 GPT 4개요
Oh, mini.
미니예요
Uh, the mini variant.
미니 변형요
So obviously the smaller models are the faster ones.
작은 모델이 더 빠르죠
No surprise there.
놀랍지도 않네요
Uh, latency.
대기 시간 때문에요
Uh, that's that's measured in the number of seconds until the first token is received.
첫 번째 토큰이 도착하기까지 남은 시간을 의미하죠
It's a nice way of capturing it.
그걸 포착하는 좋은 방법이죠
That's a good way to explain what I was talking about earlier, when I showed latency on the basic attributes.
아까 말씀드렸던 걸 설명하기에 좋은 방법이네요 기본 속성에 대한 대기 시간을 보여드렸을 때요
And you can see no surprise the smaller models are able to respond very rapidly.
작은 모델도 빠르게 반응하는 게 놀랍지 않죠
Um, and here GPT four surprisingly has improved latency over GPT four.
GPT 4는 놀랍게도 4보다 대기 시간이 개선됐어요
zero.
0명요
Many, which may be just related to the the hardware setup that it has.
하드웨어 셋업과 관련 있는 게 많아요
I'm not sure, but they're close anyway.
잘은 모르지만 둘이 친해요
And then the cheapest models, which is measured in terms of dollars per million tokens.
가장 싼 모델은 백만 달러당 달러로 계산하죠
Uh, llama 8 billion comes in cheapest Gemini 1.5 flash does well, GPT four and mini of course is very
라마 80억 달러는 제미니 1호에서 가장 싼 가격에 나온 거예요 5 플래시도 잘 팔리고 GPT 4와 미니는 물론 아주 저렴하죠
And then, uh, the, uh, Claude three haiku, um, and then GPT 3.5 turbo after that.
클로드 3 하이쿠와 GPT 3도 있어요 5 터보로 바꿨죠
And this is being shown as two separate bars, one for input cost, one for output cost.
두 개의 다른 막대로서 보여지고 있습니다 하나는 입력 비용, 하나는 출력 비용이죠
So, uh, there is then a nice little interactive ability to compare two models and see them side by
두 모델을 비교할 수 있는 상호 작용적 기능이 있어요 다른 측정법에 따라
side against different measures.
나란히 볼 수 있죠
This is showing Claude three point uh, sorry, Claude 3.0 Claude three opus against GPT four.
이건 클로드 3점 아니, 클로드 3점이에요 GPT 4에 맞서는 클로드 3집이에요
Oh, let's see if we can change this around a bit and pick 3.5 sonnet against GPT four.
비트를 좀 바꿔서 픽 3을 선택해 보죠 소네트 5번과 GPT 4번요
Oh, this is the face to face that we like to look at.
우리가 보고 싶어 하는 얼굴이죠
So here we go.
자, 시작하죠
I mean, really, it looks like generally it considers them neck and neck.
두 사람이 막상막하인 것처럼 보여요
What are they saying?
뭐라는 거예요?
88.3% for Claude, 3.5 and 88.7% for GPT four.
88살요 클로드는 3%고요 5살, 88살요 GPT 4는 7%예요
Oh.
네
So giving GPT four the edge there reasoning Claude does better coding.
클로드가 코딩을 더 잘하는 이유가 GPT 4 때문이군요
Claude does better math, Claude does worse tool use.
클로드는 계산을 더 잘하지만 도구 사용은 형편없어요
Uh, of course, what we went through in week two.
2주 차에 겪은 일요
Uh, Claude does better and multilingual Claude does better.
클로드가 더 잘해요 다국어를 잘하는 클로드
So great.
정말 좋아요
Uh, fascinating to be able to compare the models side by side like this.
이렇게 모델을 나란히 비교할 수 있다니 흥미롭네요
Um, then this table has, uh, row by row, the different models.
이 테이블에는 여러 모델이 한 줄씩 있어요
Um, and so you can come through and look at, uh, closed source models like Claude 3.5 sonnet.
클로드 3 같은 비공개 소스의 모델을 볼 수 있어요 5 소네트요
Uh, that in terms of the averages, here is the one at the at the top of this leaderboard.
평균 점수와 비교해서 1위에 오른 선수는 바로 이 선수예요
Um, what you're looking at here is MLU again, which is this metric where everything scores very well.
다시 MLU를 보고 계시는데요 모든 점수가 아주 좋은 수치예요
The one that we talked about in the initial metrics human eval for Python.
파이썬에 대한 인간 평가 지표에서 얘기했던 거죠
This is the be hard benchmark that I mentioned was the benchmark designed to test future capabilities
이게 제가 말씀드린 벤치마크입니다 모델의 능력 이상의 미래 역량을 시험하기
of models above and beyond what they're capable of.
위해 고안된 벤치마크죠
Um, but would you believe when you look at this cloud 3.5, sonnet is already scoring 93.1% in B hard,
이 클라우드 스리를 보면 믿겨지세요? 5점, 소네트가 벌써 93점을 득점했어요 B 하드에서 1%로 향후
which means that no longer is this a metric that's testing for future capabilities.
역량을 평가하는 기준이 아니라는 뜻이죠
It is very much current capabilities.
현재의 기능이라고 할 수 있죠
And cloud 3.5 sonnet is crushing it.
클라우드 스리도요 5번 소네트가 끝내줬어요
Uh, grade school math and harder math problems.
초등학교 수학이랑 더 어려운 수학 문제요
So here you see the the the the results from these different models.
여기 보시면 다양한 모델에서 나온 결과가 있어요
And something I mentioned early on that that is a bit puzzling is that cloud 3.5.
앞서 제가 좀 아리송한 걸 언급했는데요 클라우드 3 비트는 5분
Sonnet performs better than Claude three.
소네트가 클로드 3세보다 잘하네요
Opus.
오퍼스요
Um, but Claude three opus is still provided as a by anthropic as as an API and costs significantly
클로드 3권은 여전히 API로도 제공되고 가격도 3백 달러가 훨씬 넘어요
So I'm not sure why anyone would choose Claude.
5 소네트요
Three opus over 3.5 sonnet unless there happens to be some specific.
3부작 이상이에요 특별한 게 없다면 소네트 5편요
Well, it looks like in the case of, uh, of reasoning, uh, Claude three opus does do better.
논리에 관한 문제라면 클로드 3집이 더 잘했네요
So there are some, some, some ways in which it does better, but I'm not sure if it would be worth
어떤 면에서는 더 잘 팔리지만 추가 가격 포인트를 받을 가치가 있는지는
that extra price point.
모르겠어요
Um, and what you'll also see, of course, is that llama, uh, enters onto this model comparison.
그리고 라마가 이 비교 모델에 등장하는 것도 보실 수 있어요
I noticed that llama 405 billion is not shown here, and I can only imagine.
라마 4,050억 달러는 안 보이네요 상상이 안 돼요
That's because they haven't yet been able to carry out all of these tests for llama 4.5 billion, because
아직 라마 4의 모든 검사를 수행하지 못했기 때문이죠 50억 달러요, 왜냐하면
I would, of course, imagine that it far outperforms the 70 billion llama three instruct variant.
700억 라마 3 변종보다 훨씬 뛰어나다고 상상할 수 있거든요
Um.
네
And now coming down to this table, this is the one that I showed you before.
이 테이블로 내려오면 전에 보여드린 건데요
It's one place you can come to that will show you for the different models.
다양한 모델을 볼 수 있는 유일한 장소예요
What is their context, window size and what is their cost per input and output tokens.
컨텍스트, 창 크기, 입력 및 출력 토큰 당 비용은 얼마일까요?
So it's of course only comparing the um, the, the, the models, uh, where it has that data, but
물론 데이터가 있는 모델을 비교하는 거지만 굉장히
it's extremely useful.
유용해요
It's something where, uh, you would either be hunting through many different pages online, or you
온라인에서 여러 페이지를 찾아볼 수도 있고 여기 와서 한곳에 다 볼 수도 있어요
can come here and see it all in one place, and that's why you should bookmark it.
그래서 책갈피에 적어두셔야 해요
Uh, it of course, highlights that Gemini 1.5 flash has the extraordinary a million context window.
제미니 1호를 강조하죠 5번 플래시는 백만 가지 문맥을 보여주는 놀라운 창이 있죠
That is, of course, 750,000 words or so of common English, uh, almost the complete works of Shakespeare,
일반적인 영어로는 750,000단어 정도 됩니다 셰익스피어 작품의
a extraordinarily large context window.
거의 전부죠 문맥상 아주 큰 창이에요
The Claude family at 200,000.
클로드 가족은 200,000살이에요
The GPT family at 128,000.
GPT 가족은 128,000살이었죠
Which, as I said before, seems somewhat slim compared to the million in Gemini 1.5 flash.
제미니 1호의 백만 대에 비하면 다소 적은 숫자죠 5번 섬광이에요
But that's still a lot of information to be able to digest in a context window and still give a good
하지만 컨텍스트 창에서 소화해야 할 정보가 여전히 많아요 좋은 반응도
response.
주고요
Uh.
네
You'll also see some open source models in the mix here.
오픈 소스 모델도 보이실 거예요
You can see mixed trials, context window size, and that the llama three models have an 8000 token
혼합 평가판과 컨텍스트 창의 크기가 보입니다 llama 3 모델은 8000 토큰 컨텍스트 창을 가지고
context window.
있네요
And that's worth bearing in mind as you compare using open source models to their closed source cousins,
오픈 소스 모델과 비공개 소스 모델을 비교할 때 명심할 가치가 있어요
that if you need these massive context windows, then you're probably needing to go to the closed source
이런 거대한 컨텍스트 창문이 필요하다면 비공개 소스 경로로 가야겠죠
Okay, so there is then a coding leaderboard that you can look at to compare human eval and then that,
코딩 리더보드가 있는데 사람 평가를 비교할 수 있어요 그게 피지
uh, that concludes the leaderboards on the vellum web page.
웹페이지의 리더보드를 마무리하죠
There is one more to look at.
한 명 더 있어요
Of these, um, business, uh, sites, and it is called the seal Leaderboard, provided by a company
비즈니스 사이트들인데 실 리더보드라고 해요 스케일이라는 회사에서 제공하죠
Com and scale specializes in generating bespoke data sets.
컴 앤 스케일의 전문 분야는 맞춤형 데이터 세트 생성이죠
So if you are working on a particular problem and you need to have a data set, uh, crafted, curated
특정 문제를 작업 중이라면 자신의 문제에 맞는 데이터 세트를 제작하고 큐레이팅해야 합니다
for your problem, then that is something that scale com is in business for.
스케일 컴이 비즈니스를 하는 게 바로 그런 거죠
Uh, if you aren't able to use the data generator that hopefully you built as part of last week's challenge.
데이터 발생기를 사용할 수 없다면 지난주 과제의 일부로 만든 것이길 바라요
So this leaderboard has a bunch of very specific leaderboards for different tasks.
이 leaderboard에는 여러 가지 작업에 대한 아주 구체적인 leaderboard가 있어요
And there's one on adversarial robustness, which is designed, as it explains very well here on the
그리고 대립적 견고성에 관한 것도 있습니다 이 강의에서 잘 설명했듯이 시험
Learn More to, uh, test prompts designed to trigger harmful responses from large language models.
학습 프롬프트에 대한 것도 큰 언어 모델에서 해로운 반응을 촉발하도록 설계됐죠
And so there's this, specific examples of the kinds of problematic questions that are asked.
그래서 문제가 되는 질문의 구체적인 예가 있어요
And if, for example, you're looking sorry, I didn't mean to do that.
예를 들어, 당신이∙∙∙ 미안해요, 일부러 그런 건 아니에요
If, for example, you're looking to surface this as a chat as perhaps your airline customer support
예를 들어 이걸 항공사 고객 지원 챗봇으로 나타내고 싶다면
chatbot, you will care about the fact that it is robust against being taken off track and doing something
이게 궤도를 벗어나거나 뭔가 크게 잘못되지 않도록 한다는
that that could be far off the rails.
걸 명심해야 해요
So this is a useful benchmark for that purpose.
그 목적을 위한 유용한 벤치마크죠
Coding gives a more detailed benchmark for coding skills, and you can see Claude 3.5 sonnet leads the
코딩은 코딩 기술의 더 상세한 척도를 제공합니다 클로드 3을 보세요 소네트 5편이 길을 인도하죠
Um, and Mistral, of course, this is another set of boards that combines closed and open source.
미스트랄도 마찬가지로 닫힌 소스와 오픈 소스를 결합한 회로죠
And Mistral Large two um, is in that top three, uh, as an open source, uh entrant instruction following
미스트랄 라지 투가 3위 안에 들어요 오픈 소스로서 참가 강좌죠 여기
uh, here you'll see that, uh, wonderfully, the llama 3.1 405 billion.
보시면 라마 3이 있어요 1억 4,500억 달러요
They have been able to test this against instruction following.
지시를 따르지 않고도 이를 시험할 수 있었죠
And it's in second place.
2위에 올랐죠
It's ahead of GPT four zero.
GPT 40보다 앞섰어요
It's just behind Claude 3.5 sonnet.
클로드 3호 바로 뒤예요 5 소네트요
Uh, and so that is an amazing result for the world of open source and for meta coming in second place
오픈 소스 세계와 메타에 있어서 놀라운 결과입니다 2위를 차지했어요
Uh, and in math problems.
수학 문제도 풀었고요
Llama 3.1 405 B comes in third place, GPT four zero and second Claude 3.5.
라마 3요 1 405 B가 3위 GPT 40, 2위는 클로드 3이죠 5분
Sonnet leading the way for math.
소네트가 수학을 이끌고 있어요
And then there is also a leaderboard for Spanish, uh, which shows some of the results here.
스페인어 순위표도 있어요 여기 결과를 보여주죠
Uh, and Mistral is the open source front runner in fourth place with GPT four zero in pole position
오픈 소스의 선두 주자 미스트랄은 4위입니다 GPT가 4위인 가운데 선두를 달리고
here.
있죠
And Qxl.com are adding more of these business specific leaderboards all the time.
Qxl도요 비즈니스 특정 리더보드를 늘 추가하고 있어요
So come back to see what else has been added and use this as a great resource for more specific leaderboards
다시 돌아와서 추가된 다른 것이 있는지 보고 비즈니스 문제에 대한 보다 구체적인 leaderboard를 위한 훌륭한 리소스로
for your business problem.
이걸 사용하세요